Located off of the East Coast of the United
States is one of the world’s most powerful
current systems, the Gulf Stream. It distributes
a large amount of warm water from the Gulf
of Mexico and Caribbean Sea northward to
the North Atlantic Ocean.
Data from Earth-orbiting satellites equipped
with Advanced Very High Resolution Radiometers
can be used to determine sea surface temperatures.
In this false-color image, red and orange
colors indicate warm ocean water, while blue
and purple indicate colder water. The Gulf
Stream is visible as a sinuous band of red,
wrapping around the southern tip of Florida,
moving up the eastern seaboard where it
changes color to yellow and then flows into
the waters of the North Atlantic Ocean.
The position of the Gulf Stream varies once
it passes Cape Hatteras North Carolina. In
this simplified map view, the Gulf Stream
can be seen changing its position and wiggling
around in a snake-like fashion. These fluctuations
create curving loops of water known as meanders,
similar to those seen in the shapes of streams
on land.
The ocean transfers heat in a similar fashion
as our atmosphere, through something akin
to storms. These ocean storms are known as
eddies. The Gulf Stream produces eddies that
spin off of the primary current path and move
heat outward. Eddies can either have a cold
core, where the water at its center is cold,
or a warm core, where there is warm water
at its center.
Eddies are formed when rings are pinched off
as the Gulf Stream meanders. The direction
that the eddy pinches off determines whether
it has a cold core or a warm core. If the
eddy pinches off into the warm water to the
south, cold water is captured at its core.
On the other hand, if the eddy pinches off
into the colder water to the north, it captures
warm water at its core. These eddies sometimes
last for several months, providing a unique
ecosystem for marine life. Eventually, the
eddies dissipate into the surrounding water,
or, in some cases, they rejoin the Gulf Stream.
The Gulf Stream moves an impressive amount
of water and heat into the northern latitudes.
As it does so, it directly affects weather
and climate patterns over the entire globe.